The characteristics that make embedded systems operate
efficiently are also a security risk.
Embedded systems are often used to control something
physical such as a valve for water,
steam or even oil.
These devices have a limited instruction set and are
often hard coded or permanently written to a memory chip
for ease of operating the mechanical parts.
The embedded system is often connected to a corporate
network since and may operate using the TCP/IP protocol.
Yes, the same protocol that runs all over the internet.
Therefore,
it is feasible for anyone anywhere on the internet to control the
opening and closing of a valve when the networks are fully connected.
This is the primary reason for segmentation of these systems on a network.
If these are segmented properly,
a compromised corporate network will not be able to
access the physical controls on the embedded systems.
The other side of the embedded systems which also applies
to IOT devices is the general lack of system updates.
When a new vulnerability is found
in the case of most embedded systems with the programming directly on the chips,
it would require physical replacement of the chip to patch the vulnerability
for many systems.
It may not be cost effective to have someone visit each one to
replace a chip or manually connect to the chip to reprogram it.
We buy all these internet connected things because of the convenience
cameras, light bulbs, speakers, refrigerators, et cetera,
all bring some sort of convenience to our lives.
But they also introduce risk.
While the reputable mainstream brands will
likely provide updates to their devices.
When a new vulnerability is discovered,
many of the smaller companies simply don't plan to do that
as they seek to control the costs of a device.
These devices when connected to a corporate network can be an easy
internet connected doorway for a cyber criminal to access a corporate network.
If these devices are properly segmented or separated on
the network from corporate servers and other corporate networking,
a compromise on an IOT device or a compromised embedded system
will not be able to access those corporate data and systems.